Citizens, the National Convention, trusting in your courage, hereby accepts your oaths of loyalty.
The liberty of your homeland will be the reward for your efforts.
And while you defend your liberty with the force of your arms, the National Convention will defend it by the force of the laws.
The monarchy is hereby abolished.
So that, Dominic, was yet another person shouting loudly, one of many in our ongoing history of the French Revolution.
And it was specifically Jérôme Pétillan, who was president of the National Convention on the 21st of September 1792.
And obviously, the abolition of the French monarchy after centuries and centuries and centuries.
I mean, this is a seismic moment, isn't it, in the history of France?
But also...
Of Europe.
It's a massive moment, Tom.
And I think the only voice that really is appropriate to the moment is the one you did there.
I mean, because I detected more than a hint of our old friend, Jeremy Corbyn.
Is that right?
Yes, because I think that Jeremy Corbyn, he would definitely be on the side of abolishing the monarchy had he been in the French Revolution.
I think he probably regrets that he wasn't part of the French Revolution.
Yes, I imagine that is.
But he's always got Cable Street, hasn't he?
So yes, this is a massive moment in French and European history, isn't it?
Because the French monarchy, I guess, one of the oldest in Europe.
If you take it back to Clavis, who we talked about just before Christmas, didn't we?
So, yeah, I mean, that's the end of that story.
Yes, it is.
So it sends shockwaves across Europe.
We will be talking about what it means.
And of course, we'll be talking about what it means for Louis XVI.
And we'll get to his story in our final episode.
Nothing good.
But before we get to the moment when they actually do abolish the monarchy, we should set the scene a little bit, Tom.
We love setting the scene on this podcast.
Well, we do.
We did in the previous episode.
We set it in the context of the role of women, didn't we?
But shall we go back to the lads?
What are the lads up to?
Let's set it in the context of Prussians and cannons.
Oh, Prussians.
So the situation in Paris, people will remember from the last episode, but one, Paris is preparing for an attack.
There are church bells ringing.
There are cannons on the River Seine that are calling people to prepare for war.
The streets are packed with volunteers who are streaming towards the gates of the city to the front.
People are pulling down the grills of churches.
They're digging up their coffins to use as lead for musket shots.
There are everyday contingents of troops marching through the National Assembly, singing patriotic songs and shouting slogans and stuff.
So it's all excitement.
Jeremy Corbyn would actually have loved it.
But it's not a Sandbrook vibe, is it?
Not really a Sandbrook vibe, I would say.
Although slightly more Sandbrookian, somewhere out there.
Yes, the doer defenders of reaction.
Yes, the woods and valleys to the east are my people, are the Prussians.
The Duke of Brunswick, the real hero of this story.
So on the 20th of September, so that's the day before the reading that you began with, the new National Convention meets for the first time.
Now, some listeners, if they've made it all the way through the series, may be like, I've lost track of all the different assemblies and whatnot.
So if you remember, there had been the stormy, the tuileries.
In August.
And since then, France has been in political limbo.
And they have basically summoned yet another semi-constituent assembly.
This one has unlimited powers to remake the nation.
And it is by far the most democratic yet.
So all men over the age of 21, except for servants, can vote.
Because we talked about that last time and you said that you weren't in favor of it.
Yeah, I don't agree with it at all.
I'm with the Duke of Brunswick on this.
I think it's a dangerous innovation.
Failed experiment.
Yes, exactly.
So it's a very complicated electoral system, a series of electors and kind of almost like an electoral college.
And then they choose the 749 deputies.
But as you said, Tom, the turnout is really poor.
So in some places it might be a fifth, but generally it's probably one in 10.
And the reason for that, I think, is there's a war on.
So it's, you know, people have got other things in their mind.
But it's also harvest time.
So in the.
The countryside, people have definitely got other priorities, and they actually, a lot of people are now completely confused.
They're probably even more confused than listeners to the podcast.
They have no idea what's going on.
They don't know who anybody is.
Yeah, well, yes, exactly.
And also on top of that, there's quite a lot of intimidation, isn't there?
There is.
That's another aspect to it.
Of course.
Remember, we did that episode about mad elections in Britain where, you know, people, people being carried on chairs and whatnot.
And.
And lots of throwing of cats.
Well, similarly, in France, for the national convention, the voting is public and it is oral.
You vote, you know, you say who you want to vote for.
So if you want to vote in favor of a royalist party, you're basically standing up and saying, I am a reactionary traitor to La Patrie in front of all your fellow villagers.
I mean, it's not who are like holding clubs and stuff and sort of leering at you in a sinister way.
So clearly a lot of people just don't want to turn out.
So in Paris, the voting has coincided with the September massacres.
That's what we began this little kind of miniseries with.
So the atmosphere is very grim because as people are voting, there is the kind of stepping over corpses, right?
The dull sound of hacking coming from inside the walls of the converted convent just down the road.
So what is worse?
The second round of voting is held at the Jacobin Club.
So if you are a royalist or reactionary.
This is not the ideal place to go and to sort of pin your colors to the mast.
And that round of voting, the Jacobin Club, they've got a lot of kind of electors, but they start by agreeing that they'll purge all electors who are foyant, who are moderates or who are royalists.
So 200 electors are kicked out.
There's 800 left and they vote for 24 deputies.
And of those deputies, a lot of those are very big revolutionary names.
So the top of the list, number one, their top choice for Paris is Robespierre.
And then you've got people like Danton, Desmoulins, Santerre, the butcher, the sans-culottes who'd led the attack on the Tuileries.
Marat, for the first time, this firebrand radical journalist, he is going to have a seat in the convention.
So there will be a place for the most extreme, the most violent, the most paranoid revolutionary sentiments.
And there's a place, isn't there, for the worst man in the entire history of the French Revolution?
Yeah.
The erstwhile Duke of Orléans, the cousin of Louis XVI.
Philip Egalité.
I mean, we've talked about this before.
This is Prince Harry calling himself Harry Diversity or something, renaming himself.
And actually…
No, Harry Equity.
Harry Equity, yeah.
While living in his palace.
Yeah, that's what he'd call himself.
Yeah, Harry Equity.
Anyway, so everybody goes to the Tuileries on the 20th of September to register.
And they do so in an atmosphere of apocalyptic dread because they know that 140 miles away,
the Prussians are there and that their troops, their France's troops, have basically caught up with the Prussians.
And the Duke of Brunswick, just to remind people, has said that he is going to inflict a biblical fate on Paris.
He has, yeah.
A vengeance which will be forever remembered, or words to that effect.
So, yes.
Now, of these guys who've turned up to register, about half of them are lawyers.
So if you're…
We've got a lot of lawyers who are members of Arrested History Club, so they will love all this.
They will say this is a very good sign.
There's also loads of doctors, loads of civil servants, loads of actors, journalists.
They're very young, by and large.
About half of them are under 40.
About a quarter of them are under 35.
The younger they are, the more committed and more militant they are, by and large.
So, you know, these aren't…
A lot of them have got experience in kind of local governments and stuff, but these aren't incredibly seasoned people.
They are excited and excitable, I think it's fair to say.
Kind of quite a student union vibe.
Definitely.
I mean, this is the birth of the student union, really, isn't it?
I think it probably is, yeah.
Motions, all that kind of stuff.
Yeah, they love it.
And they're there all night, you know, just endlessly arguing and showing off in that student union.
And drinking.
Exactly.
Next day, 21st of September, they assemble at the riding school, the Manège, for their first proper session.
And this is the bit that you started with, Jérôme Pétion, because they've come straight to the central question.
Let's reboot France.
And it must be a…
There's an actor, of course, called Collot de Bois.
He ends up on the Committee of Public Safety later on.
He says, let's just abolish the monarchy right away.
No need for referendums and all that stuff.
Let's just go for it.
Some of the deputies say, really?
No, no, you wouldn't let the people have a say on such a massive question?
And then the Bishop of Blois.
So this is an interesting thing, because again, it complicates the slightly sort of stereotypical sense of the French Revolution.
Because it's a bishop, Henri Grégoire, who says,
Kings are in the moral world what monsters are in the physical world.
Their courts are the workshops of crime and the lairs of tyrants.
In other words, no referendum.
Let's just get rid.
And they vote.
And then, of course, as so often happens in these kinds of scenarios, very student union.
Once people work out which way the wind is blowing…
They all pile in.
Yeah, they all pile in.
So they make the vote unanimous.
They all start shouting, vive la nation.
They're all terribly excited.
The world has started again.
But Dominic, just to pick up one, one thing that is intriguing, and it's a kind of absence is that there isn't a kind of formal proclamation of the Republic.
There's no official decree kind of installing it.
And I just mentioned that because in the next episode, when we come to the trial of the King, I think that is significant.
And I think that that is something that frames what will happen with the trial and the execution of the King, because although it is a new beginning, although they've had the vote.
It's kind of, they know what they're getting rid of, but they don't yet know what they're establishing.
Yeah, I think that's a very fair point, actually, that there is a sense of, there's a sense of historical time beginning again, but they don't really know what they all want.
Because I suppose, Tom, they don't all want the same thing as we shall see in this episode.
So if you enjoy political factionalism, this is definitely the rest is history episode for you.
Anyway, one of the interesting things about the French Revolution that we've talked about so much is the way it faces two ways.
On the one hand, they're looking back to the Roman Republic.
As you have done.
Described so many times.
And on the other hand, they're genuinely thinking this is not just a whole new chapter, but it's basically a new, a new volume in world history.
So it's, they say from September the 20th, all state documents must bear the date year one of the French Republic.
So this is where we get the beginning of the sort of French revolutionary calendar, the numbering system year one, year two, and so on and so forth.
But of course, whether they actually get.
Beyond year one is not in their hands.
It depends on events out on the battlefield.
So let us now, let us leave Paris, turn the camera and turn the camera.
Exactly.
You know how my mind works.
So remember where we got to the Prussians have been marching all the way west from the border.
They've got to the, the Argonne forest that's 130 or so miles away from Paris.
It's pouring with rain.
Very Agincourt scenes, Tom.
There's only one man.
There's only one man who can stop them.
And that man is a guy called general Charles Francois Dumouriez.
So listeners may remember he's this kind of grizzled, ex secret agent, ex seven years war veteran who was foreign minister under the Girondins.
He got France into this mess in the first place.
And basically he's in charge of the Eastern front.
He really wanted to, he loves fighting Belgians.
He loves attacking Belgium.
That's his dream.
He wants to liberate Belgium.
The convention has basically said, forget about Belgium.
Like there's a, there are a load of Prussians advancing on Paris, get to the valley of the Marne and stop them.
There's a lot of maneuvering and faffing around in the ever kind.
Do you want to, to go into detail about that?
I, do you know what I could, I could, but I won't because I don't want to try the patience of our less military minded listeners.
Exactly.
How many divisions are there on both sides?
Loads.
So to cut a very long story short, the two armies end up faffing around and maneuvering, and basically they end up on the wrong side of each other.
So the Prussians are nearest Paris and Jumurier is behind them with his back against the Argonne forest.
Now the Duke of Brunswick could just ignore Jumurier and could have just dashed on, couldn't he to Paris?
He could, but he doesn't want to do that because he, that would mean Jumurier could cut his supply lines, basically cut him off from the German states.
And his men are very muddy and it's pouring rain, they're knackered, they're short of food, they're ravaged by illness.
It feels a little bit Henry the fifth before Agincourt, and he says, right, what we'll do is we'll stop here, we'll turn, we'll finish off Jumurier, and then we can secure our supply lines, and then we can go on to Paris.
Jumurier is massively outnumbered, but he had very good news for him.
So on the 19th, the day before the national convention, they meet to register.
He is reinforced by a second French army under General Kellermann.
Who has a German name.
He has a German name, very confusing.
Yeah, that is confusing.
So these troops that they have, by the way, everybody always thinks this is a great victory for kind of people in red bonnets shouting about the revolution.
But it's not, is it? They're all basically royalist officers and seasoned veterans and so on.
They are, they are. These are like regular troops.
And they also have a brilliant kind of new cannon.
They do indeed. They have a very exciting new cannon.
We love military technology on this podcast.
They have new lightweight cannons that were specially designed after the French had shamed themselves in the Seven Years' War.
It's Britain.
Exactly. They'd lost to everybody, hadn't they?
It'd been a kind of world war.
They'd been fighting the Prussians or whatever.
So on the 20th, so this is the day that the national convention were registering.
On the 20th, it's a misty, foggy morning.
Kellermann, outside this windmill, outside the village of Valmy, he lines up his men on this ridge.
And he's got his lovely, lightweight cannon.
This could be a very friendly way to design something.
Instead of three bacon deep cannons that he's very keen to show off.
The Prussians start firing with air cannons.
Kellermann fires back with his, there's hundreds of guns blazing away through the fog.
Now, do you know who was fighting for the Prussians?
I do.
It was Goethe, the great German writer.
The greatest German writer.
Germany's top writer, Goethe.
He was fighting with his patron who was Grand Duke Karl August Sachs Weimar.
Was he actually fighting?
I always wondered about that.
Yeah. Because I thought he just kind of tissueed everything, but that's important, isn't it?
you know he'd gone in the train and was writing a poem well this is the thing i think there's no
evidence i think of him actually shooting anybody i can't imagine him in a in a uniform that seems
very odd he must have been wearing uniform though because as we will discover he's exchanging banter
with the lads of the of the battalion and stuff um goethe said i mean you expect great pros from
a great writer don't you do you know what he said the earth literally trembled it was a clash of
titans france a land of contrasts anyway the earth is literally trembling goethe can't believe
it what scenes this goes on for hours and hours and hours then the prussians eventually say okay
enough we've definitely softened the french up now and bronzer extends his infantry advancing in
these kind of long lines blue uniforms they're advancing up the hill they're convinced that the
french are about to collapse but no general kellerman takes off his hat with his trickler
cockade and he lifts it up on his sword and he shouts
vive la nation and then the french will start singing the satira one of their revolutionary
songs but interestingly not the marseillaise which apparently there's no evidence that they
say that no so that may be another uh pointer to the fact that these are not uh the kind of
the radicals the uh the cutting edge revolutionaries as yet right exactly i think
the revolutions would love to rewrite this this is soncolot singing the marseillaise
and and indeed they do in subsequent years but that's not true at all
so they're blasting away the prussians keep coming the prussians can't believe the french
are so full of vim and vigor and then basically the prussians waver and brunswick says call them
back call them you know enough and the french against all the odds and all expectations because
they've performed so abysmally at the beginning of the war they have actually they haven't quite
won but they have survived to fight another day so it's kind of scraping a result in the final match
of a group round in the world cup
kind of a bit like that
uh i think it is a bit like that but after you've it's it's a it's the draw that you
need that keeps you alive in the group i think is what it is but that's because it's come
unexpectedly it's fated as a great victory it's fated as a great victory exactly that's exactly
what it is the prussians actually have killed more frenchmen the french have killed prussians
but for the first time the prussians have been stopped they haven't been able to dislodge the
french and their re the reactions of the two sides could not be more different so the prussians are
absolutely gutted they can't believe it
doesn't goethe he makes a famous comment uh in a very grandiloquent way saying that this is
what is it something like gentlemen you have witnessed the the dawning of a new age i felt
you were gearing up to do him as jeremy corbyn there which would have been a shame so goethe
says there's a wonderful scene it's the great vanity of great writers he says they all sat
alone around this fire they're all really miserable they couldn't meet each other's
eye and he says um everybody asked me what i thought about the events of the day as i
quote my little sayings had often interested or amused our little company and i think what an
unsufferable bore he must breed to all the other soldiers so he said to everybody from this place
and from this day forth commences a new era in the world's history and you can all say you are
present at its birth now so i'll tell you something i don't believe he did say that
i think that's far too good to be true and he writes this a considerable time afterwards so i'm
suspicious of gertrude here i think he's playing fast and loose with the uh the facts is too good
that's what writers do dominic it is it is what they do anyway for the french this is massive so
that there's a peasant soldier who writes to his father and he says um been electrified with a new
courage that will make despots tremble oh liberty oh equality oh my country what a wonderful
transformation it's like listen to theo i mean if peasants are writing like that after the battle
there may be gertrude and gertrude and gertrude and gertrude and gertrude and gertrude and gertrude and
there is saying that kind of thing maybe tom i mean maybe they're all you know massive effusions
they all feel that this is titanic i don't know i just yeah no fair that's fair so lots of people
say gosh this is a tremendous victory for the for the new republic for our revolutionary virtue and
when of course when the news reaches the convention they're all waving their hats in the air and
delighted and they say absolutely brilliant history has begun again it is a new chapter
in the story of the human race and dominic i've got a question which is
that the news reaches paris um after the monarchy has been abolished is there a feeling that this
victory has been won because france is now a republic do you think there's something like
that yeah we've got rid of the king and the traitors and immediately we start winning yeah
as soon as we as soon as we took those blokes into the court the courtyards of various prisons
and dispense summary justice and as soon as we lock the uh king up in the temple fortress
surprise surprise we start winning battles you know
at demonstrandum the king was a traitor and was undermining the war efforts and that is what
happened uh with the first democracy when athens um establishes its democracy having thrown out its
tyrants they immediately start winning battles and presumably people would have been aware of this
maybe this is an ironclad law of history tom or maybe it's just a coincidence anyway well it is
because by because they actually win the battle before the proclamation of the republic right
yeah well said they don't really win the battle it's just a draw so the you would think that this
would be good for them in general because it's the sound of the people talking about uh
you know you know bon army harm sense of harmony yeah come on let's bury that into ideological
hatchet work together for the common good you would be wrong because actually from the beginning
i know you wouldn't be wrong tom i know you know that what's gonna happen the convention is riven
by the most unbelievable faction fighting so basically there are three blocks and maybe we
don't need to spend an eternity discussing them but a little bit of context first of all you have
the Brissot and the Gironde. So if you remember, these are not really a Parisian party. They're
a party of the kind of big provincial cities like Bordeaux. Because that's where Gironde
comes from, isn't it? It's the Northern Bank. Exactly. They're all hanging around having dinner
with Madame Roland in her apartment and swapping witty aphorisms. And they've basically got about
150 deputies in the convention that will always support them. And they can call on some independents
to give them a majority. Then you have the great mass of people who are kind of in the middle.
They are called, they're either called the Marsh, which seems a very, you know, it's not very,
I wouldn't want to be part of the Marsh. Les Pères Centristes. What's that? Centrist Dads.
Oh, right. Okay. Very good. Yeah. Well, they're not really Centrist Dads either because everybody's
now on the left. But they are the Marsh or the Plain, people call them, because they sit in the
middle of the hall. And they basically...
Yeah, they can lean one way or the other. But at this point, they are generally swayed by the
Girondeaux. And then you have the Radicals on the far left. They're called the Mountain,
the Montagnards. And they sit high up in the left of the hall, hence the Mountain.
There's about 200 of them, 150 to 200. They're very Parisian, Robespierre, Danton, Marat.
All the famous guys, the ones that people have heard of.
They dominate the Jacobin Club now because the Girondins don't bother turning up to it.
And they...
They also appeal to two groups. Very young deputies are much more likely to be Montagnards.
They're likely to be kind of more impatient, more ambitious, more radical.
And this is the first manifestation of a sense that runs right the way up to the present day,
that the young are inclined to back more radical solutions on the left, right? I mean,
this is the first manifestation of it.
I think that's absolutely right. They also appeal to deputies, interestingly,
who come from very isolated kind of places, who've basically been the one radical in their village.
Who therefore feel very embattled. And when they arrive in Paris, they're delighted to find friends.
And that their being embattled has made them more radical, I guess.
That must be very exciting for them.
Oh, yeah. I think there's a definite sense of excitement.
And of the Montagnards, basically, now we think of them as being a party ruled by the triumvirate of Robespierre, Danton, and Marat.
I mean, they really are the big three of the French Revolution, aren't they?
The triumvirate, you might almost say.
But they're not like a triumvirate.
They actually don't really get on with each other.
Well, Robespierre hates Marat, doesn't he?
Robespierre despises Marat. Won't have anything to do with him. Like, refuses to have anything to do with him.
I think because Robespierre is so chilly and he's so worried about his wig and his kind of boniness.
He's got great skin.
Yeah.
And Marat doesn't wear a wig. Has terrible skin. Awful. Sits in baths.
Right. Both Danton and Marat have terrible skin, don't they?
Danton is too busy, like, stuffing himself with, like...
Chicken legs.
Yeah. And also taking brown envelopes of cash.
Marat is just shouting about, like, killing everybody and being very over the top and stuff.
So actually, they're all quite suspicious of each other, these three.
They don't work together as a tight-knit unit.
I guess the other question is, are these kind of ideological political parties of the kind that we would recognize today?
And the answer again, I think, no.
The Montagnards and the Girondins, to outside observers, seem to have loads in common.
You know, they're all Republicans.
They all believe in the war, all of that stuff.
There are two things.
I think that are really important.
The differences.
So one of them is the idea of the people.
The Girondins, because they're kind of merchant class from Bordeaux and stuff, they basically think that people like them should be running the revolution.
You know, people who go to literary salons and quote poetry to each other.
Yeah.
Whereas Robespierre and the Montagnards, they think, they're suspicious of that.
They are pure populists.
They're all about the common people, the virtues of the street.
You know, the people of Paris know better.
Yeah.
A poor urchin knows much better than a, you know, it's that kind of.
It's Rousseau, isn't it?
It's very Rousseau.
It's almost very Christian.
Is it not?
I'm surprised you didn't say that.
Of course.
But I mean, you know, this is what I think about everything in the French Revolution.
That's true.
Yes, that goes without saying.
The other thing that's perhaps a little less Christian is the Montagnards are much keener on violence.
No, but you see, I think that is pretty Christian.
Virtuous violence.
Yeah.
Okay.
Crusades, inquisitions.
Let's just assume you're thinking of everything.
No, I don't think of everything because obviously you can have non-Christian violence, but I
think the idea of violence being virtuous.
Yeah.
That's where it's coming from.
Yes.
As you'd expect, because this is, you know, 18th century France and displays of violent
virtue are everywhere.
Yeah.
Fair enough.
So obviously the most visible sign of virtuous violence has been the September massacres,
which the Montagnards were all for.
But the Girondins are actually a little bit conflicted about the September massacres.
They've been Robespierre.
I thought all this was brilliant.
You know, he loved the attack on the Tuileries.
He loved the September massacres.
He thinks the fact that Girondins are being a bit squeamish shows that they are suspects,
counter-revolutionary and all that kind of thing.
Tom, I can see you're itching to say something.
What is so interesting and fascinating about this is that you see for the first time the
manifestation of political trends that just repeat and repeat and repeat.
And surely what is happening with the Girondins and the Montagnards is the notion that people
on the left can be...
Yeah.
...outflanked to their left.
And therefore are always moving leftwards to try and avoid that.
And so the radicals of one month can suddenly find themselves the reactionaries of the next
month.
And it means that there's an impetus always to go further and further.
Whether you were backing, you know, the people are always right, or whether you were saying
virtue is manifest in violence.
If you start saying, oh, I'm not sure about that, then immediately you are a reactionary.
Absolutely.
And that is a trend that you see again and again and again.
I mean, throughout the history of 19th century.
Yeah.
And right, you know, right the way up to the present day.
Absolutely.
You're totally right.
That sort of ratchet effect.
And in fact, I was just thinking if somebody missed a couple of episodes of the series,
you know, if they'd skipped ahead, they'd be like, hold on, those people were on the
far left two episodes ago.
Now you're describing them as, you know, counter-revolutionary reactionaries.
Because as you say, the center of gravity is always moving leftwards.
What's on the Girondins' mind as well, by the way, is the fact that during the September
massacres.
Yeah.
There is some evidence that Robespierre and Marat had actually toyed with the idea
of killing them too.
So Robespierre, on the day the massacres had broken out, the 2nd of September, he had been
giving a speech in the commune, the sort of city council of Paris, in which he had said
that the Girondins were secret agents of the Prussians and perfidious intriguers working
against French liberty.
Now anyone who's listened to the whole of this series will know how bonkers that is,
because the Girondins were the key people in getting France into the war in the first
place.
But of course, at the time, everybody believes in this idea of the mask of patriotism, that
the more patriotic you appear to be, the more likely it is that you are in fact a traitor.
So the commune had issued a warrant for some of the Girondins' arrest, which was never
carried out.
But Brissot and Roland and these people, they know about this and they say, my God, Robespierre
wants to kill us.
He wanted to kill us and it's just luck that he didn't.
And so they become convinced, well they are now convinced, that basically it's kill or
be killed.
So in that sense, right from the moment the convention meets, which is 21st of September,
it's not like a normal parliament that we would know today because there is no sense
of pluralism.
There's no sense that they're going to be having discussions and you win some, you lose
some, all that kind of thing.
No sense of a loyal opposition?
None.
So by definition, this is about virtue versus corruption.
It's about the Republic versus counter-revolution.
To be a dissenter is to be a traitor.
And so I think from the very first moment they take their seats, it is obvious there
is absolutely going to be a showdown and that whoever loses that will probably end up on
the guillotine.
And if you had to put your money on somebody at this point, September 1792, you would probably
put it on the Girondins.
They have a bit more of a majority, they have a bit more self-confidence, they control
the presidency of the convention.
And so right from the beginning with the September massacre so fresh in their minds, they say,
right, let's settle this once and for all, let's do this.
And right away they go for the Montagnards' throats.
Wow.
Well, I think that is too much excitement for one half of an episode.
So I think we should take a break here and when we come back, we will see what the upshot
of this Girondin attempt to win.
To take down the Montagnards actually is.
Hello, welcome back.
We left you at a moment of high drama.
The Girondins are about to take on the Montagnards in the national convention.
Dominic put people out of their misery.
What happens?
So they make their move, Tom, two days after the Battle of Valmy, 22nd of September.
The convention has only really been up and running for a day and a bit.
And a dozen speakers, one after the other, Girondins get up and lay into the Montagnards.
And they won't.
Their plan is to convince the convention the Montagnards are traitors and they should
be arrested and thrown out of the convention.
They say they are anarchists, they are murderers, they are levelers, interestingly.
Oh, right.
A word that will be very familiar to people who know about 17th century England.
But don't they also compare them to Caesar, Crassus, and Pompey?
They do.
The first round version of ancient Rome.
They're very promiscuous with their historical analogies, I think it's fair to say.
Because Brissot says, on the one hand, he says they're the hydra of anarchy.
They want to level everything.
And on the other hand, he says Robespierre, Marat, and Danton are the new Crassus, Caesar,
and Pompey, exactly as you said.
And Robespierre and Danton say, oh, this is absolute nonsense, you know, I don't even
like him.
I have no...
We're not a triumvirate at all.
Marat, he obviously is...
He's making his debut, effectively, in front-line politics.
Wow.
What a way to do it.
And he says, I'm not a traitor, but if you're accusing me of trying to set up a dictatorship,
well, I'll be frank with you.
I think a dictatorship would be brilliant.
I'd love a dictatorship.
And he's then saying...
Yes.
He pulls a gun out of his pocket, and he holds it to his own head, and he says, if you vote
to condemn me, I will blow out my brains in front of you.
Better than threatening to blow out the brains of Girondins, basically.
I guess so.
People are very impressed by this.
They say, well, this obviously shows that Marat's a tremendous fellow.
And the result of this is that they're not kicked out.
So the Montagnards have made a bit of a mistake here.
I was about to say they've wounded but not killed their opponent.
They've barely even wounded them.
Yeah.
I mean, if you're going to shoot at the king, you better kill him.
Exactly.
So it is clear from this point that this feud is only ever going to get worse.
And a few weeks go by.
The Girondins basically are sort of constantly niggling at the Montagnards, but never bringing
them down.
Also, the Girondins, as time goes by, they're actually beginning to lose a bit of support
from the plain, from the independent people, because the independent people actually are
a bit sick of this.
And also, the Girondins are quite corrupt, and they're very overbearing, and they're
very kind of hungry for power and bossy.
Of course.
They go to all their dinner parties, haven't they?
They go to their dinner parties.
High-flying dinner parties.
Yeah.
Exactly.
Inviting the normal people.
Right.
And if you're just a bog-standard deputy from provincial France, you're sick of being lectured
by Brissot and having him slagging off the Montagnards and stuff, you just become very
impatient with all this.
And I think the Girondins know this.
So towards the end of October, they decide to have another go.
And this time, they will just go for Robespierre, and they'll go for him personally.
And they get a newspaper editor called Jean-Baptiste Louvet to stand up and accuse Robespierre of
trying to make himself dictator, of having a personality cult.
Now, again, they reach for a Roman parallel, interestingly.
Of course they do.
So Louvet deliberately models his speech on Cicero unveiling the Catiline conspiracy.
And of course, that's the analogy that everybody knows.
They've all grown up with it.
They've all done it at school.
It's been on their minds.
How long will you abuse our patience, Robespierre?
All of that stuff.
Exactly.
And Louvet says, come on.
France has a choice.
There are only two parties.
And France must choose.
There is the party of us, the Girondins, we're the party of philosophers.
And on the other hand, there is the mountain, they're the party of murderers.
Put it like that.
Yeah, exactly.
If I was facing attack from the Prussians, and I had to choose one of those two parties
to represent me, I definitely wouldn't choose the philosophers.
But do you know who's there for this?
Well, you do know, because I know you've got the notes.
But also I know this, because I'm a big fan of his, is the great poet William Wordsworth.
He's basically on his gap year, isn't he?
Yeah, he is.
He's on a holiday.
Well, he's not on holiday.
He's graduated and doesn't know what to do with himself.
So he's gone off to France, supposedly to improve his knowledge of French.
But actually, he's having an affair with a woman in Orléans, got her pregnant.
But that would improve your French though, surely.
Yes, it would.
Give us a bit of poetry, Tom.
I know you love a bit of Wordsworth.
When a dead pause ensued and no one stirred, in silence of all present, from his seat Louvet
walked single through the avenue and took his station in the tribune, saying, I, Robespierre,
accuse thee.
Now, that line is actually a bit confusing, isn't it?
Because it makes it sound like Robespierre is claiming to be-
Exactly.
I don't want to diss Wordsworth, one of our greatest ever poets.
Wordsworth lets himself down there with his lack of clarity.
So this is in the prelude, which he writes much later when he's become a counter-revolutionary
and a massive reactionary.
Shall I carry on?
Do.
We'd love that.
A bit more poetry?
Yeah, I love it.
Okay.
Well is known.
The inglorious issue of that charge and how he who had launched the startling thunderbolt.
So that's Louvet.
The one bold man whose voice the attack had sounded was left without a follower to discharge
his perilous duty and retired lamenting that heaven's best aid is wasted upon men who to
themselves are false, which is a long way of saying that Louvet's attack doesn't work
and he doesn't get the support that he'd been expecting.
And it's all a bit of an embarrassment and a letdown.
It is an embarrassment.
Exactly.
Wordsworth in a very convoluted way is quite right.
And actually Rob Spierre completely wins the day.
So a week later, Rob Spierre, he buys his time and then he makes his response.
And he says, um, I have encouraged violence, he says, but I did it because it was the only
way to save the country.
And he says to everybody, do you want to have a revolution without a revolution?
I mean, we have to, you know, I did it and I was right to do it.
Because people may remember when we, when we talked about the, um, guillotine, um, that,
uh, Rob Spierre was against capital punishment.
But he is now saying that the, the travails of the Republic are such that the real crime
would not be to support the elimination of those who threaten France and the nation.
And as we discussed in the September massacres episode, a majority clearly agree
with that.
They think we're at war, you know, we've always executed people.
It's not like public executions and the public display of violence is a, is a novelty.
It's completely reasonable.
It's reasonable for us to use violent measures to preserve the Republic.
And so Rob Spierre wins the day.
He gets torrents of applause in the convention.
Brissot and the Girondins are kind of fuming, they're sort of like sort of cartoon characters
kind of clenching their fists with braid.
You pesky Montagnards are kind of on the benches.
And Brissot writes to Dumouriez and he says, this is absolutely intolerable.
He says, I spend all my time fighting these miserable anarchists.
That's a direct quote.
When I should be concentrating.
On the uprising of the entire planet, I mean, which is a bonkers thing to say, but quite
Trotsky, isn't it?
It's very Trotsky, but you can see why he's saying it because we're now six weeks
after the battle of Valmy and since then, Tom, there have been some unbelievably dramatic
scenes on the battlefield.
As Dumouriez managed to invade Belgium, which you said was, is a long-term kind of plan.
Excitingly.
Yes.
Oh, bless him.
So for once, somebody in the story has actually got what he wanted.
So basically.
That's what's happened.
I know you love military history, Tom.
The Prussians have been hanging around outside Valmy pouring with rain after this kind of
draw and the Duke of Brunswick eventually says, right, listen, we don't want to be cut
off from our supplies.
We're obviously not going to get to Paris.
Let's cut our losses, head back towards Germany for the winter.
So in scenes of great sort of degradation and misery, which kind of Goethe writes about,
he withdraws all the way back and he even goes all the way back across the river Rhine.
Now that really matters because what that means is that the Western bank of the Rhine is
now completely undefended with German cities and towns on it, it is completely undefended
from the French.
So by late October, the French who are on their uppers a bit ago, and now advancing
on German cities, places like Mainz, Worms, Frankfurt, and out of these German cities,
the Prince bishops and the electors and the, all of these big wigs.
They're kind of fleeing as fast as they can with all their kind of Germanic books and
whatever marzipan on carts.
So this is the point of what Brissot is saying to de Meurier is that this is now an international
revolution.
Right.
The world lies open before us because the French, by the way, in the long run, this
will be a massive moment in European history because it's basically the birth of German
identity and German nationalism because loads of people who'd waited, couldn't wait for
the French revolution to get to Germany.
I mean, I don't know.
As soon as the revolution does turn up, they say, oh God, this is terrible.
Well, these French people kind of living in our houses, looting all our stuff and bossing
us around.
And so you get the German identity.
You can argue to some degree dates from this moment as a kind of political force.
Anyway, the French don't just stop at the Rhine.
They're advancing everywhere.
So they invade the Swiss Federation.
They're heading for Geneva.
They invade Savoy and they take all the lands west of the Alps, which, and they create a
new department called Mont Blanc.
They also seize the capital.
They take the county of Nice.
We always think of Nice as, I mean, most people think of it as French.
It's actually been part of Savoy since 1388.
And so all these kinds of little medieval aberrations are being swallowed up by France
and becoming part of France.
So like Avignon as well had already gone.
Yeah.
Avignon.
Exactly.
But above all, Belgium.
So Dumouriez had always dreamed of this.
He beats a small Austrian army at a place called Jemappes, which is just south of Mont,
on the 6th of November.
And the Austrians have to pull back.
He takes Mons.
He's in Brussels by the 14th of November.
By the end of November, I mean, this is the extraordinary thing, the seesaw momentum.
He has taken Liege and Antwerp and he is heading towards the borders of the Dutch Republic.
And Dominic, by this point, there is a lot of singing of the Marseillaise.
Loads.
Exactly.
It accompanies the invasion, the victories, all kinds of things.
I think this is the moment actually, when you can say that patriotic revolutionary fervor
is born, really.
Born in victory.
This is the point at which you have patriotic festivals across France, sort of feasts and
bonfires and people singing things like they're singing the Marseillaise in the streets.
And again, it's a manifestation of the fact that now France is no longer a monarchy
and is a republic.
Suddenly they're winning.
Yeah.
Absolutely.
But here's the thing, right?
They're not just winning.
They're winning victories now.
And because the Prussians and the Austrians had basically not bargained for this, over
extended themselves, not properly prepared, the French are now winning victories that
are really unprecedented in the last few generations.
Victories that eclipse even the victories of Louis XIV.
And so deputies back in Paris are now beginning to ask themselves, well, where will we stop?
Where would the revolution stop?
Because of course they've always thought of it as not just a French nationalist project,
but a universalist one.
Again, this is what Brissot is saying, that this is a global issue.
He's the arbiter of the world.
Exactly.
Some people say, well, our borders, our obvious borders are geographical, the Pyrenees, the
river Rhine, the channel, the Mediterranean and so on.
But other people are saying, well, really?
I mean, if we stand for liberty, if we stand for these kind of timeless, eternal values,
why would we stop at some mountains?
Why wouldn't we go beyond?
And have they not enrolled as French citizens, people in foreign countries who
are particularly enthusiastic for the revolution?
Like Tom Paine?
Tom Paine would be the famous example.
On the 19th of November, they vote.
France will assist anybody, anybody who wants to, and I quote, recover their liberty.
And a month later, they agree that everywhere French armies go, they will take the revolution
with them.
So that means they will abolish feudalism.
They will attack the privileges of the Catholic church.
They will institute a Republican system.
So it's a war on the monarchies of Europe.
So this has never happened before in European history.
Yeah.
States have fought wars with each other, of course, and taken each other's territory.
But the idea that you would go into somebody's country and completely rewire their system
so that it looks like yours, ideologically reboot them, this to a lot of people is profoundly,
profoundly shocking.
So Cromwell hadn't done that?
No.
I mean, there'd be no sense of, let's export the English revolution.
Exactly.
And what is more, I mean, I think this is very French.
They decide that they will make everybody else pay for this.
So there's a guy called Pierre.
Who's a Protestant merchant from name.
And he says, listen, there's an obvious way to fund the, this when we occupy a given country,
they should be so grateful for their Liberty that they should pay us a tax to pay for their
own occupation.
And the convention, this is a, this is an absolutely, absolutely great idea.
Now you might think this sounds very over the top and hubristic, but they, I think really
believe in this.
Yeah.
So he was standing there in the convention sort of November, 1792, and he is saying,
we will liberate Naples.
We will liberate Spain.
We will liberate Poland.
We will be in Berlin.
Probably this time next year, we can go all the way to Moscow.
You know, it's like they're basically drunk on their own rhetoric.
His friend Vernieu, remember we had him talk about the, um, there was a great quote from
him.
He was a great orator talking about the declaration of war in the first place.
He now says this will actually be the last war.
This will be the end of history.
Men have died.
He says, but they have died so that no men will ever die again.
I swear to you in the name of the universal fraternity, which you are creating that each
battle will be a step towards peace, humanity, and happiness for all mankind.
So I think if that's what, if that's what they're bringing, it's fair enough to get
people to pay for it.
Very good.
I mean, the thing is nobody has ever talked about this in European history before, you
know, when France was fighting its wars in Italy.
In the early 16th century, nobody said this is the war to end all wars.
This will bring a new age of happiness.
They just said, brilliant, let's pile into Milan and Luton pillage.
You know, did Henry the fifth say this in the hundred years war?
Did Edward the third?
Of course they didn't.
But the dream of a universal peace is of course, I mean, you know, we know where that's coming
from.
We do indeed.
But of course there is, among other things, there's a very obvious problem that they have,
which is, um, it's a problem left over from before.
For the Republic.
And it's that they have still in their midst, not just any old traitor, but the traitor
of traitors, you know, a rallying point for counter-revolution.
It's the erstwhile King.
It is the erstwhile King.
It's Louis Capet.
Well, so, so that is what they call him Louis Capet because the, um, the man who
is elected King of the Franks at the end of the 10th century is Hugh Capet.
So that's where.
The name of the Capetians comes from.
It's not actually his name.
And in the next episode where we look at the trial and execution of the King, we'll explore
why they call him, uh, Louis Capet and not Louis Bourbon, but I just, I just intrude
with that, but they call him Louis Capet.
That never occurred to me before that obviously that isn't really his name.
No, it's not his name.
And he, and, uh, Louis objects very strongly to being called Capet, but we will explore
this tomorrow.
That's tantalizing.
Tom, if I wasn't already a member of the Restless History Club, I'd sign up now.
So that I, cause I'd have to wait.
So just, uh, the last sort of five minutes or so before Theo explodes with rage that
we're going on too long.
Where has Louis been all this time?
He's been in the temple in this medieval keep.
He's been with Mary Antoinette, his sister, Elizabeth, and his two children.
Um, they'd been reading loads of books that they basically living like a middle-class
English family during COVID in lockdown.
So Louis and Mary Antoinette have been homeschooling the children.
They've been teaching them to recite kind of great.
Reams of Racine and cornea and stuff.
Great French dramatists, uh, Louis loves his geography.
So they've been coloring in a map of the new departments of France and tracing and doing
all this stuff.
It's actually quite sweet.
They play badminton in the garden and at night, uh, Louis, this will please you, Tom.
He reads passages of Roman history to them, but presumably not the establishment of the
Republic.
No, I don't think so.
But apparently he reads passages that somehow mirror their own predicament.
So people who've been locked up, but are very noble.
And long suffering and all this kind of thing.
They are quite tightly restricted.
Mary Antoinette's not allowed to sew in case she's sewing a code.
Louis is not allowed to shave, you know, because people are aware that he might kill himself
and the guards, it's very like the Romanoffs in 1918, the guards were always kind of scribbling
graffiti on the wall that shows a fat man being hanged or guillotined or something.
So that's a bit ominous for Louis.
Now the convention.
You might say, why do they have to take any precedence?
Proceedings against him at all.
Cause he's just a citizen now.
This is the point of Louis Capet.
He's just like anyone else.
But there are, of course, there are two reasons.
One is if they really think he's been betraying them to foreign enemies, they really ought
to punish him.
And number two, they know there are loads of Royalists in France.
They can't leave such an obvious focus for counter-revolutionary rebellion alive.
And the son culottes on the streets of Paris still blame him, remember for the fighting
at the Tuileries in the Swiss guard.
And all of that sort of business.
They have a huge discussion about whether constitutionally they are allowed to put him
on trial because under the old constitution, if the king transgressed, it laid down what
you do and you remove him from office.
But once you do that, it's done.
So can they punish him further?
And basically they get a constitutional lawyer, a guy from Toulouse called Jean-Baptiste Mailly.
And he says, Louis is clearly guilty of terrible crimes.
And the law of nature overrides the constitution.
The constitution actually was given by the nation.
And if the nation gives the constitution, the nation has the right to withdraw it.
And the law of nature demands that Louis is punished.
And this is a crucial moment, isn't it, in the history of what will happen over
the next year.
The idea that if you follow nature, then you can't do anything wrong.
No matter where it is.
No matter where it leads.
There again, very Rousseau.
Very Rousseau.
So they have a sort of debate about how this will work.
A few people, a very small group of kind of what you, I suppose you would say people on
the right of the convention, on the right of the Girondin group say, I just think we
should leave him alone.
Let's not do this at all.
But most people say, we should probably have a trial.
There are some Montagnards, whoever, who say a trial is mad.
We should just kill him straight away.
He doesn't even deserve a trial.
And the most famous one of those, a character who we should now introduce, is a young man,
the youngest deputy in the whole convention.
He's only 25 years old, and he stands up to make his maiden speech in November.
So this guy is called Louis-Antoine Saint-Just.
He's from a small town in Picardy.
He's basically a massive Robespierre fan.
He's been sending him fan mail since 1789.
And I kind of think about Saint-Just that here's the point at which Rousseau and romanticism
meet.
He's got long, lank hair.
He's got an earring.
He's very pale.
He's never seen smiling or laughing.
He's Shelley with political power.
Yes, I guess he is.
Was it Shelley who was pursued by his classmates around Eton?
Yes.
The Shelley hunt.
Yeah.
I would have loved to have seen that with Saint-Just, because I hate Saint-Just.
He wrote an enormous poem, didn't he, about his sexual frustration.
Surprise, surprise.
Yes, he did.
And he prides himself, he basically loves Robespierre, and he prides himself on being
even more virtuous, more emotionless, more logical.
Rationalist.
Yeah, than Robespierre.
That rationalism and virtue are to be equated.
Yes.
And again, this is the birth of something that over the course of the 19th century will
actually become quite chilling.
It's the kind of thing Dostoevsky was obsessed by.
Yeah.
Saint-Just is the founding paradigm of the terrorists that you get in Dostoevsky's
novels.
He absolutely is.
But again, he loves the idea, the very word terror.
It's a very Saint-Just word.
But his rationalism, his kind of icy rationalism, is the icy rationalism of somebody who is throbbing
with suppressed emotion.
Isn't he?
I mean, basically.
He's an incel.
He is a total, he is a man who just needs to go for a walk, meet some girls.
Hang out with Danton.
Yeah, exactly.
Danton, show him a good time.
Anyway, of course, that relationship doesn't end terribly well, does it?
No.
And Danton.
Perhaps not coincidentally.
So Saint-Just gets up and he says, there was no need for a trial.
Because the point he says is that Louis is not guilty because of anything he's done.
He's guilty.
And this really brings out your point.
This absolutely anticipates so much of the revolutionary stuff of the 19th and 20th centuries.
Saint-Just says he's guilty because of what he is and what he has been.
A virtuous republic cannot allow somebody who has been a king to live.
And I quote, no one can reign innocently.
Every king is a rebel and a usurper.
So there's no middle ground.
This man must reign or die.
He must die to assure the repose of the people.
Right.
And Dominic, that is the crucial, crucial line that opens up, I think, the proper understanding
of the trial and execution of the king.
Because there is no foundational moment for the republic.
There is no proclamation.
And that is because the king still lives.
So therefore the death of the king becomes the kind of the baptism of the republic.
And I think that that is why Saint-Just dies.
And I think that that is why the most famous speech is so memorable and so significant.
Yeah, I think that's a really good point, Tom.
Because it does.
It is one of the two or three most famous speeches of the entire revolution.
It makes Saint-Just's name.
And it also, as you say, seems to serve as a kind of departure point, as a punctuation
point in kind of France's constitutional journey.
Anyway, the funny thing about this speech is actually it doesn't work because they decide
they will have a trial.
So while they're making the plans for the trial, just before we get into that, just
as they're finalizing the plans for the trial.
There is a really, really important development.
Monsieur Roland, the husband of Madame Roland, the interior minister, who is a Girondin,
on the 20th of November, is taken into the Tuileries Palace by a locksmith called Gamin.
Gamin was the guy who had taught the king all about his locks.
And Gamin says to Monsieur Roland, no one knows this, but I'm going to show you something.
And he takes him and he shows him a secret iron safe hidden behind the paneling.
Roland opens it.
And it's full of confidential papers and documents.
And he now makes a terrible mistake, a mistake that I think will kill him.
He takes the papers out and he goes through them himself in secret.
He doesn't share them with anybody.
And then he goes to the convention.
He says, well, I've made an amazing discovery.
I have found all these confidential documents and they, I can, let me tell you, there's
some pretty interesting things in them that will incriminate some of you.
And you will, you won't be laughing then.
And lots of deputies are really shocked.
And frightened and outraged at this, especially the Montagnard.
They're like, what are these documents?
How do we know that you haven't forged them?
Doctor them.
Exactly.
They're absolutely furious.
So all this will come back to really haunt Roland and the Girondins.
But in the meantime, the documents prove two things.
First of all, they prove now beyond any possible doubt that Louis was conspiring against the
revolution.
He was in touch with the Austrians.
He was writing to counter-revolutionary groups.
He was doing all of this kind of stuff because his signatures are all over these papers.
His fate is sealed from this point that he has done.
I think the second thing they, the documents also prove beyond any possible doubt that
all that stuff about the mask of patriotism, which we've discussed as though it's so paranoid
and such a mad conspiracy theory is indeed quite accurate because one of the great heroes
of the early revolution, Mirabeau, another man with terrible skin, by the way, he's clearly,
there's.
There's loads of letters from him showing that he was conspiring against the revolution,
taking loads of money from the courts and you know, his, his reputation is shredded.
They go and take his ashes out of the Pantheon.
They take his bust out of the Jacquemin club.
They're like, well, this proves the point.
Can't trust anyone.
Can't trust anybody.
So few days after this, the 1st of December, the convention votes, first of all, anyone
who calls for the return of the monarchy, anyone who, who makes any, and I quote infringement
on the sovereignty of the people.
Which is very satisfyingly vague.
If you are, if you're a big fan of revolutionary terror, yeah, we'll face punishment by death.
And two days later they vote that this man, Louie cap.
We can discuss his name next time will be brought before the national convention to
answer for his crimes.
And Rob spear gets up at the tribunal and he says, remember your task is not to pass
a sentence for and against a man.
It is to defend the safety of the public.
And to take an act of national providence.
I pronounce this fatal truth with regret, but Louie must die because the homeland must
live.
Amazing stuff.
So, uh, Dominic and everyone, um, the scene is set Louie will be brought to trial.
Um, will he be convicted?
If he is convicted, what will his fate be?
There is only one way to find out, and that is to tune into the next episode.
If you simply can't wait, then you can go to the rest is history.com and sign up there.
But either way, we are approaching the climax of this particular stage of our series on
the French revolution.
So we'll see you very soon.
Bye.
Au revoir.